Hello, English learners.
你好，英语学习者。
Welcome back to another podcast here at EnglishPod.
欢迎回到 EnglishPod 的另一期播客。
My name is Marco.
我是 Marco。
And I'm Erica.
我是 Erica。
And today we have a fun dialogue.
今天我们有一个有趣的对话。
That's right.
没错。
Well, maybe the language in this lesson you won't use every day, but it's fun, it's interesting,
嗯，也许这节课的语言你不会每天用到，但它很有趣、很有意思，
and it's a little bit on the lighter side.
而且稍微轻松一些。
That's right.
没错。
Today we're going to be looking at baby talk.
今天我们要看看婴儿语。
So we're going to see some of these words that aren't really words.
所以我们会看到一些其实不算单词的词。
They're not real words that you can find in the dictionary, but native English speakers
它们不是你在字典里能找到的真正单词，但英语母语者
use them when they're talking to little babies.
在跟小宝宝说话时会用到它们。
Yeah, in many languages, there's a rule for how you make baby talk words, right?
是啊，在很多语言里，都有怎么造婴儿语词的规则，对吧？
Right.
对。
But in English, we don't have really clear rules about how you make a word a baby word.
但在英语里，我们并没有很明确的规则来说明怎么把一个词变成婴儿词。
So we're going to teach you a few of these baby words.
所以我们会教你几个这样的婴儿词。
Exactly.
没错。
So before we listen to the dialogue, why don't we take a look at vocabulary preview.
所以在听对话之前，我们先来看看词汇预览。
Vocabulary preview.
词汇预览。
Okay, we have two words here we're going to hear in the dialogue.
好的，我们有两个词会在对话里听到。
And the first one is diaper.
第一个是 diaper。
Diaper.
Diaper。
Okay, so a diaper, a baby uses a diaper.
好的，diaper，宝宝用尿布。
That's right.
没错。
It's a piece of cloth or material that you put around the baby so that it can go to the
它是一块布或材料，你把它围在宝宝身上，这样他就能
bathroom and not make a mess.
上厕所而不弄脏。
Okay, a diaper.
好的，尿布。
Now we also have another word that we commonly use in the English language, it's Nana.
现在我们还有另一个英语里常用的词，是 Nana。
Nana.
Nana。
So Nana is the name we call a grandmother.
所以 Nana 是我们称呼祖母的名字。
Right, so an informal name, just like in Spanish, we would say something like Abue or Abuelita.
对，一个非正式的名字，就像在西班牙语里，我们会说 Abue 或 Abuelita。
Or in Italian, you might say Oma.
或者在意大利语里，你可能会说 Oma。
This is another way that we can call a grandma or granny.
这是另一种叫 grandma 或 granny 的方式。
Nana.
Nana。
Okay, so Nana.
好的，所以是 Nana。
Why don't we listen to the dialogue for the first time, let's see how these new parents
我们第一次听一下对话吧，看看这对新父母
are talking to their little baby using baby talk.
是怎么用婴儿语跟小宝宝说话的。
Honey, the baby's up again.
亲爱的，宝宝又醒了。
It's your turn.
轮到你了。
I went last night.
我昨晚去的。
Fine.
好吧。
Hello, little baby.
你好，小宝宝。
Why are you crying, little baby?
你为什么哭啊，小宝宝？
Oh, I see, you made a doo-doo.
哦，我明白了，你拉臭臭了。
What's going on, hon?
怎么了，亲爱的？
Why is the baby crying?
宝宝为什么哭？
The little baby made a doo-doo.
小宝宝拉臭臭了。
What a good boy.
真是个好孩子。
Let's get this icky diaper off you.
我们把这个脏尿布脱下来吧。
Look at what I have here.
看看我这儿有什么。
Mickey Mouse jammies.
米老鼠睡衣。
Oopsie daisy, did the little baby just tinkle all over daddy?
哎呀呀，小宝宝是不是刚尿了爸爸一身？
Yes, he did.
是的，他尿了。
You just made a wee-wee all over daddy.
你刚尿了爸爸一身。
Hold still while I change his yucky diaper.
别动，我来换他这脏尿布。
What's going on in here?
这儿怎么了？
Oh, look, it's Nana.
哦，看，是奶奶。
Say hi to Nana.
跟奶奶打个招呼。
Oh, he's so adorable.
哦，他太可爱了。
I could just eat him up.
我真想把他吃掉。
Okay, say hi to Nana.
好了，跟奶奶打个招呼。
Hi, Nana.
嗨，奶奶。
Okay, say bye to Nana.
好了，跟奶奶说再见。
Time to go beddy-bye.
该睡觉觉了。
Okay, well, that was pretty cute, wasn't it?
好了，嗯，那挺可爱的，是吧？
A cute dialogue.
一个可爱的对话。
The baby seemed to be cute and, well, everyone's excited about the new baby.
宝宝看起来很可爱，而且，嗯，大家都为新生儿兴奋。
But they use some really interesting little words that are pretty unfamiliar.
但他们用了一些挺有意思的小词，这些词相当陌生。
So let's look at them now in Language Takeaway.
所以我们现在在“语言要点”里看看它们。
All right, so as we mentioned before, these words aren't actually words.
好的，就像我们之前提到的，这些词其实不是真正的词。
You won't find them in the dictionary.
你在字典里找不到它们。
Right, but you'll hear them commonly when people are talking to babies and you might
对，但你在人们跟宝宝说话时会经常听到，而且你可能
see them in a movie or something like that.
会在电影或类似的东西里看到它们。
So why don't we get started with the first one?
所以我们从第一个开始吧？
All right, the first word that may seem a little bit strange.
好的，第一个词可能看起来有点奇怪。
The father said, hello, widdle baby.
爸爸说，你好，小宝宝。
Widdle baby.
小宝宝。
Okay, widdle.
好的，widdle。
So widdle is just a baby talk way of saying little.
所以 widdle 只是 little 的婴儿语说法。
Little, that's right.
Little，没错。
Now the father saw that the baby was crying because he made a doo-doo.
现在爸爸看到宝宝哭是因为他拉臭臭了。
The baby made the doo-doo, not the father.
是宝宝拉臭臭，不是爸爸。
Right, the baby made a doo-doo.
对，宝宝拉臭臭了。
A doo-doo.
拉臭臭。
Okay, so basically a doo-doo is when the baby poos or poops in the diaper.
好的，所以基本上 doo-doo 就是宝宝在尿布里拉屎。
Okay, so, you know, sometimes you go to the bathroom and it might take a little bit longer.
好的，所以，你知道，有时候你上厕所可能会花更长时间。
Exactly.
没错。
That's because of the doo-doo.
那是因为拉臭臭。
The doo-doo.
拉臭臭。
Right, the actual technical or maybe the proper English word for this would be defecate.
对，实际的技术性说法或者也许更正式的英语词是 defecate。
Okay, so make a doo-doo.
好的，所以是拉臭臭。
All right, now our third words are interesting because he said icky diaper.
好的，现在我们的第三个词很有意思，因为他说了 icky diaper。
That's right, an icky diaper.
没错，脏尿布。
And then he also said yucky.
然后他还说了 yucky。
So we've got two words here that mean the same thing, icky and yucky.
所以我们有两个意思相同的词，icky 和 yucky。
And basically means disgusting.
基本上意思是恶心的。
Right, something that's really, really not nice.
对，一些非常非常不好的东西。
So you would say icky or yucky.
所以你会说 icky 或 yucky。
Now these words have other similar words.
现在这些词还有其他类似的词。
We might recognize ick or yuck.
我们可能认识 ick 或 yuck。
Right, so you would use ick or yuck if something is disgusting, but when you're kind of talking
对，所以如果某样东西很恶心，你会用 ick 或 yuck，但当你跟
to a baby, you would say icky, yucky, smelly.
宝宝说话时，你会说 icky、yucky、smelly。
Yes, the adjective.
是的，形容词形式。
Now our next word, the father said he has some Mickey Mouse jammies.
现在我们的下一个词，爸爸说他有一些米老鼠睡衣。
Jammies.
睡衣。
Okay, so what are jammies?
好的，所以 jammies 是什么？
Well the word jammies is short for pajamas.
嗯，jammies 这个词是 pajamas 的简称。
Okay, pajamas, so the clothes that you put on when you go to sleep.
好的，睡衣，就是你睡觉时穿的衣服。
Jammies.
睡衣。
All right, and now for our last two words, they mean the same thing as well.
好的，现在最后两个词，它们意思也一样。
The little baby tinkled all over daddy.
小宝宝尿了爸爸一身。
So to tinkle.
所以是 tinkle。
And then his mom said a wee-wee all over daddy.
然后他妈妈说了 wee-wee，尿了爸爸一身。
You made a wee-wee.
你尿了。
Okay, so tinkle and wee-wee.
好的，所以 tinkle 和 wee-wee。
Usually also going to the bathroom, but this time to pee.
通常也是上厕所，但这次是撒尿。
To pee, exactly.
撒尿，没错。
To urinate.
小便。
A wee-wee.
尿尿。
So the verb to tinkle and the noun a wee-wee.
所以动词是 tinkle，名词是 wee-wee。
Very good.
非常好。
So these are the words that we have for you today in language takeaway.
所以这些就是今天在“语言要点”里为你准备的词。
As you can see, they're kind of cute and very common when you're talking to babies and you
如你所见，它们有点可爱，而且在你跟宝宝说话时非常常见，你
know, you have to be a little bit nicer.
知道，得稍微温和一点。
All right, so why don't we listen to the dialogue another time, a little bit slower, and you'll
好的，所以我们再听一遍对话，稍微慢一点，这样你
catch these words a little bit easier.
会更容易抓住这些词。
Honey, the baby's up again.
亲爱的，宝宝又醒了。
It's your turn.
轮到你了。
I went last night.
我昨晚去的。
Fine.
好吧。
Hello, little baby.
你好，小宝宝。
Why are you crying, little baby?
你为什么哭啊，小宝宝？
Oh, I see.
哦，我明白了。
You made a doo-doo.
你拉臭臭了。
What's going on, hon?
怎么了，亲爱的？
Why is the baby crying?
宝宝为什么哭？
The little baby made a doo-doo.
小宝宝拉臭臭了。
What a good boy.
真是个好孩子。
Let's get this icky diaper off you.
我们把这个脏尿布脱下来吧。
Look at what I have here.
看看我这儿有什么。
Mickey Mouse jammies.
米老鼠睡衣。
Oopsie daisy.
哎呀呀。
Did the little baby just tinkle all over daddy?
小宝宝是不是刚尿了爸爸一身？
Yes he did.
是的，他尿了。
You just made a wee-wee all over daddy.
你刚尿了爸爸一身。
Hold still while I change this yucky diaper.
别动，我来换这个脏尿布。
What's going on in here?
这儿怎么了？
Oh, look, it's Nana.
哦，看，是奶奶。
Say hi to Nana.
跟奶奶打个招呼。
Oh, he's so adorable.
哦，他太可爱了。
I could just eat him up.
我真想把他吃掉。
Okay, say bye to Nana.
好了，跟奶奶说再见。
Time to go beddy-bye.
该睡觉觉了。
All right.
好的。
So now that we've seen those great words, let's take a look at two phrases that we're
所以现在我们看过了那些好词，让我们看看两个短语，
going to look at now in Fluency Builder.
我们将在“流利度构建”里学习。
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建。
So the mother didn't really want to get up and look after the baby.
所以妈妈不太想起床照顾宝宝。
She said, it's your turn.
她说，轮到你了。
It's your turn.
轮到你了。
So when she says, it's your turn.
所以当她说，轮到你了。
That means you should do it now.
意思是现在该你做了。
Right.
对。
So she's basically saying, now you have to do it.
所以她基本上在说，现在你必须做。
I did it last time, so now you have to do it.
我上次做了，所以现在你必须做。
It's your turn.
轮到你了。
That's right.
没错。
It's your turn.
轮到你了。
And, well, the Nana, the grandmother, she was really, of course she really loves this
而且，嗯，奶奶，她当然非常爱这个
little baby, and she said, I could just eat him up.
小宝宝，她说，我真想把他吃掉。
I could just eat him up.
我真想把他吃掉。
Now does she want to really eat him?
现在她真的想吃掉他吗？
No, of course.
不，当然不。
Of course not.
当然不。
So what does she mean by this?
所以她这么说是什么意思？
This is a phrase we often use with very cute things.
这是一个我们经常用在非常可爱的东西上的短语。
It just means, oh my God, he's so cute.
它只是说，哦天哪，他太可爱了。
Okay, he's so cute that I wish I could just hug him and kiss him a lot.
好的，他可爱到我希望我能好好抱抱他、亲亲他。
Yes, we might use this with babies or maybe with puppies.
是的，我们可能用在宝宝身上，或者也许是小狗身上。
I could just eat him up.
我真想把他吃掉。
All right.
好的。
So great two phrases that we've just taken a look at.
所以我们刚看了两个很棒的短语。
Let's go back to our dialogue for the last time, and then we'll come back and talk a
让我们最后一次回到对话，然后我们会回来再
little bit more about these babies.
多聊聊这些宝宝。
Honey, the baby's up again.
亲爱的，宝宝又醒了。
It's your turn.
轮到你了。
I went last night.
我昨晚去的。
Fine.
好吧。
Hello, little baby.
你好，小宝宝。
Why are you crying, little baby?
你为什么哭啊，小宝宝？
I see you made a doo-doo.
我看到你拉臭臭了。
What's going on, hon?
怎么了，亲爱的？
Why is the baby crying?
宝宝为什么哭？
The little baby made a doo-doo.
小宝宝拉臭臭了。
What a good boy.
真是个乖孩子。
Let's get this icky diaper off you.
我们把这个脏尿布换掉吧。
Look at what I have here.
看看我手里有什么。
Mickey Mouse jammies.
米老鼠睡衣。
Oopsie daisy.
哎呀，小心点。
Did the little baby just tinkle all over daddy?
小宝宝是不是刚尿了爸爸一身？
Yes he did.
是的，他尿了。
You just made a wee-wee all over daddy.
你刚在爸爸身上尿了一泡。
Hold still while I change his yucky diaper.
别动，我来给他换掉脏尿布。
What's going on in here?
这里怎么了？
Oh look, it's Nana.
哦，看，是奶奶来了。
Say hi to Nana.
跟奶奶打个招呼。
Oh, he's so adorable.
哦，他太可爱了。
I could just eat him up.
我真想一口把他吃掉。
Okay.
好了。
Say bye to Nana.
跟奶奶说再见。
Time to go beddy-bye.
该睡觉觉了。
Okay, so they are obviously new parents.
好吧，他们显然是一对新父母。
They've just had a baby, so they're excited about him waking up.
他们刚有了宝宝，所以对宝宝醒来很兴奋。
They're all excited about the baby and how he wakes up and everything.
他们对宝宝以及他醒来的样子等等都特别兴奋。
But an interesting thing, the baby was sleeping in another room.
但有趣的是，宝宝当时在另一个房间睡觉。
In English-speaking countries, people have sort of two different opinions about how you
在英语国家，人们对如何
should sleep with your baby.
和宝宝一起睡有两种不同的看法。
Some people want to have the baby in the bed with them, right?
有些人想让宝宝和他们一起睡在床上，对吧？
But some people think, no, the baby should definitely sleep in its own room.
但有些人认为，不，宝宝应该自己睡在房间里。
Okay, in another room in a crib.
对，在另一个房间的婴儿床里。
Yeah.
是的。
Right.
没错。
I think this is a very important issue because many people consider that it's a good thing
我认为这是一个非常重要的问题，因为很多人认为
for the baby to sleep with the parents and it feels safe and you can make sure the baby's
宝宝和父母一起睡是件好事，这样宝宝会感到安全，你也能确保宝宝
okay.
没事。
And it's easier for waking up to feed the baby and change his diaper.
而且醒来喂奶和换尿布也更方便。
Exactly.
完全正确。
And well, if the baby is sleeping with its parents, it might not wake up as much.
而且，如果宝宝和父母一起睡，可能不会醒得那么频繁。
But other people think if you let the baby sleep with the parents, the baby will become
但其他人认为，如果让宝宝和父母一起睡，宝宝会变得
kind of spoiled and not a very good baby.
有点被宠坏，不是个好宝宝。
Right.
没错。
It might become too dependent on the parents.
可能会变得太依赖父母。
And for example, if you ever want to go out or leave the baby with a babysitter or when
比如，如果你想出门或把宝宝留给保姆，或者当
the baby starts maybe preschool or kindergarten, it might not be really independent.
宝宝开始上幼儿园或学前班时，可能就不太独立。
So why don't you tell us what you think?
那么，你为什么不告诉我们你的想法呢？
Do you think it's a good idea to allow a baby to sleep with you or should it sleep in its
你认为让宝宝和你一起睡是个好主意，还是应该让宝宝睡在
own room?
自己的房间里？
Yeah, you can tell us at our website EnglishPod.com where you can also ask any questions you have
是的，你可以访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com，在那里你也可以提出任何关于
about the language in this dialogue.
这段对话中语言的问题。
All right, guys.
好了，各位。
So we'll see you there and until next time.
我们到时候见，下次再见。
Thanks for downloading and goodbye.
感谢下载，再见。
Goodbye!
再见！